Guide to the UH Women's Studies Program and Friends Collection
University of Houston Libraries
UH Women's Studies Program and Friends Collection
1984-2011
1991-2011
2000-007
University of Houston. Women's Studies Program
4.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection consists of administrative materials such as meeting invitations and agendas, minutes, financial reports, bylaws, and events sponsored by the Women's Studies department as well as newsletters published by the Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies and various ephemera and memorabilia.
Historical Note:
The Women's Studies Program at the University of Houston is an interdisciplinary academic field that analyzes and investigates women's roles, needs, history, and contributions to humankind. Women's Studies at UH was established in the summer of 1991. The Program offers an interdisciplinary undergraduate minor and an interdisciplinary graduate certificate -- both consist of courses drawn from the humanities, fine arts, law, and social and health sciences. The mission of the Friends of Women's Studies is to support the University of Houston Women's Studies Program through campus and community activities, as well as financial and volunteer efforts. The central focus of the Friends is the Women's Archive and Research Collections (WARC), a unique collection of documents from active and historical Houston area women's organizations, individuals associated with these organizations and local women's oral histories.
WARC, housed at the University of Houston Libraries' Special Collections Department, opened in October 1996. The WARC collecting area focuses on the roles of women and women's organizations that have made some impact on the lives of Houston area women. As it grows, WARC is expanding to statewide scope.
Collections in WARC include those focused on cultural development and social action, philanthropic, civic and professional associations, women's health issues, violence against women, minority women's groups, and a professional athletic franchise. WARC also includes the papers of several prominent Houston women. The collections document the ways that women have united to achieve their goals, the range of their concerns, and the impact they have had on the world around them. WARC also creates and preserves Texas women's oral histories through the Living Archives series, which features interviews with notable Houston women. The research collections support significant scholarly work on women's issues by students, faculty, and visiting professors and promotes awareness of women's contributions to culture through speakers, conferences, and other activities.
The Friends of Women's Studies provides financial assistance to graduate and undergraduate students and faculty and provides funds for graduate assistantships to continue processing and expanding collections donated to WARC. Scholarships are available to both undergraduates and graduates; UH faculty members may apply for doctoral fellowships and summer fellowships. An annual travel grant is awarded to a Women's Studies faculty member presenting research at conferences and a Student Essay prize for essays on a women's studies topic. Long range plans include a conference on Houston women's history and the endowment of a chair.
Note Author: Pavan Sirsi, 2003 (and edited by Kristen McAlear, 2011)
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston. Women's Studies Program
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Bylaws (administrative records); Correspondence; Financial records; Fliers (printed matter); Invitations; Pamphlets; Photographs
Acquisition Information:
Donations by Women's Studies Program and Carey Shuart, 2000-2003.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Barbara Karkabi Papers
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of administrative materials such as meeting invitations and agendas, minutes, financial reports, bylaws, and events sponsored by the Women's Studies department as well as newsletters published by the Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies and various ephemera and memorabilia. The bulk of the papers are dated between 1991 and 2011, but a few publications and clippings date to 1980s. The most recent papers include invitations to events organized by the Friends of Women's Studies, such as the annual Table Talk luncheon and other events sponsored by the Friends of Women's Studies and the UH Women's Studies department.
The records are arranged chronologically and divided into series by year, although the first series contains the records from the first 3 years of the UH Women's Studies due to a paucity of documents. Subsequent series correspond to a single year of operation. This chronological arrangement is intended to continue expanding as more materials from UH Women's Studies and the Friends of Women's Studies become available. Each series is divided topically into 8 standard sub-series, except where no such material exists for certain sub-series within a given year: UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents; Friends of Women's Studies business documents; Women's Archives and Research Center; Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial documents; General Correspondence; Newsletters; Events, Programs and Scholarships; and Clippings and publications.
Detailed List of Contents
- 1984-1993
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Feminist reading group surveys, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Photo of post-doc Jennifer Parchesky, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Survey on Black and Chicana feminism, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Women's Studies faculty biographies, C.V.s, and publications, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Women's Studies minor survey, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Related organizations and conferences, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Information about courses and people in UH Women's Studies, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Courses, notes, calendars, and brochures, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - UH Women's Studies Community Outreach Board
    - Organizational documents, minutes, board member profiles, related correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - Proposals and background research, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Houston area repositories and archives list; Phillips, Faye, "Developing Collecting Policies for Manuscript Collections," American Archivist (47.1), 1984, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter organizational documents, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Women's Studies newsletters 1.1, Spring 1992, Fall 1993, June 1993; UH Herald, Fall 1993, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Flyers and handouts, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings and Publications
    - Feminist reading lists and articles, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Marketing Premiums for Promotion of Women's Studies
    - Friends of Women's Studies logo printouts (Ovs box 4, Folder 1)
    - Friends of Women's Studies tote bag (Ovs box 4, Folder 2)
    - Women's Studies tote bag (Ovs box 4, Folder 3)
    - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies t-shirts (Ovs box 4, Folder 4)
    - 50/50 by 2000 and 50/50 by 2020 buttons (Ovs box 4, Folder 5)
- 1994
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Course planning documents, organizational charts and documents, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Background of WS Program research - Bunting Institute (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Background of WS program research - Members survey (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Background of WS program research - Phone survey (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - UH Women's Studies Community Outreach Board Administrative Documents
    - Member lists, minutes, and other documents (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Handwritten minutes and notes (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC background research (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - WARC Prospectus documents (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - WARC founding correspondence (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Women's Studies account summaries (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Fall/Winter 94 (3), Spring 94; Friends of Women's Studies newsletter - Oct/Nov 1994; Extra originals; other related documents (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Flyers, Lecture Series programs, schedule of events, C.V.s of speakers (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Photos from events and award ceremony (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings and Publications
    - Women's interest articles and clippings (Box 1, Folder 31)
- 1995
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Documents related to the search for a program director (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Marketing committee information and meeting notes (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Mission, goals, organizational chart, and informational flyers (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Women's Studies course syllabi and information (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - UH Women's Studies Community Outreach Board Business Documents
    - Membership and flyers (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Bylaws, including drafts (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Meeting notes, task forces, and procedures (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC planning committee documents (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - WARC prospectus, collection development policy, proposal narrative, and other background research (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Women's Studies program account summaries, expense reports, fiscal year gift account, and price lists (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1995 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Newsletters
    - Newsletter drafts, article suggestions, and issues, Spring/Summer 1995 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Living Archives (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Hidden Treasures party photographs (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Flyers, planning documents, calendars, schedules of events, scholarship applications for miscellaneous events (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Clippings and Publications
    - UH publications (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Newspaper clippings and other publications (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Beijing Conference on Women newspaper clippings (Ovs box 4, Folder 6)
- 1996
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Bylaws, reports, reviews, flyers (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Meeting notes, January-April 1996 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Meeting notes, June-September 1996 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - Collection development policy, sample finding aids, deed of gift forms, floor plan, women's organization lists (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Members, minutes, and informational surveys (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Budgets, expense lists, gift accounts, budget memorandums (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters
    - Friends of Women's Studies newsletter - Dec. 95/Jan. 96; UH Women's Studies newsletter - Sept. 96, Winter 96 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Events, Programs and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous event calendars, flyers, and handouts (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Living Archives (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 1997
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Announcements, overview of UH Women's Studies, and survey of students seeking a Women's Studies minor (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Affiliated women's studies organization - Rice Women's Research Center (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Bylaws, board meeting minutes, board meeting agendas, memoranda, member lists (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC proposals, organizational and background documents (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Budgets, expense reports, and fundraising (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Mar. 97, Sept. 97; Women's Studies newsletter drafts: Fall 96/Spring 97, Spring 97, Spring/Summer 97 draft, article drafts; Friends of Women's Studies newsletter April/May 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Events calendars, flyers, invitations, and related correspondence for miscellaneous events (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Living Archives photos - "Women in TV" (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Shuart Retirement party photographs (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Conference on Architecture photographs (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Sands of Time party photographs, 1997, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - General photographs (Box 2, Folder 19)
- 1998
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Women's Resource Center organizational documents, proposals, and background research (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Board meeting agendas and minutes, flyers, Friends of Women's Studies fact sheets and planning documents, membership lists (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC progress reports, donation guides, and other business documents (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Budgets (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Spring 1998, Summer 1998 and draft (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous flyers for events and scholarship winners list (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Living Archives - Women in sports, Eleanor Tinsley at the Menil Museum (Interviewed by Andrea Jorgenson of Houston Chronicle), miscellaneous flyers (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 1st Table Talk photos, clipping, related documents, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 1997-1998 Essay Contest - Lee, Tina - "Women and spirit possession" and Cook, Rebecca - "Gender differences in depression" (Box 2, Folder 29)
- 1999
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - List of Women's Studies courses (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies board meeting minutes, member lists (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC collection development committee and progress report (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Budgets (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Spring 1999 (2), Summer 1999 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous event flyers (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Living Archives flyers and photographs (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - 2nd Table Talk and related events - flyers, invitations, and photos (Box 2, Folder 37)
- 2000
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies flyers, members list (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC table talk display photos, WARC progress report (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Spring 2000 (3), Summer 2000 (2) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Flyers and photos of scholarship winners (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Living Archives flyers (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 3rd Table Talk (Box 2, Folder 43)
- 2001
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - 2001 post-doc - Carol Williams application, C.V., letters of recommendation, research proposal (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies board meeting minutes and agendas (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Budgets (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Newsletters
    - UH Women's Studies newsletter - Summer 2001 (2) (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous event flyers (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Living Archives flyers (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - 4th Table Talk invitations, photos, conversationalists information, and related correspondence (Box 2, Folder 50)
- 2002
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies membership directory (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC collection development policy documents (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Summer 2002, Spring 2002 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Event flyers (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Living Archives flyers (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - 5th Table Talk photos and invitation (Box 2, Folder 56)
- 2003
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies membership directory, strategic plan for development, meeting minutes (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC pamphlets and collections queue (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Summer 2003 (4), Spring 2003 (2) (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous event flyers, photo from lunch at Houston racket club (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "New trends in women's studies" six week course packet (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Living Archives flyers (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - 6th Table Talk (Box 2, Folder 63)
- 2004
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies information booklet, membership flyer (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Spring 2004 (2), Winter 2004-05 (3) (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous event flyers, Dr. Carol Williams book signing photos (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Living Archives flyers (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - 7th Table Talk program and invitations (Box 3, Folder 1)
- 2005
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies meeting agenda, Spring 2005 membership directory, information circular (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter, Fall 2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - The Everybody Ball and other miscellaneous event flyers and mailings (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Living Archives (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 8th Table Talk program and invitations (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 8th Table Talk photos (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - 21st century motherhood conference photos, program, and Houston Chronicle article (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Friends of Women's Studies art contest CDRs and marketing circular (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 21st Century Motherhood t-shirts, posters, tote bag (Ovs box 4, Folder 7)
- 2006
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Cross listed courses for 2006 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies Spring membership directory, fact sheet (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC 10th anniversary CDR, WARC collections list (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - Operating budget (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondence
    - CDR of e-mails - Houston Women's caucus banners project (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Fall 2006 (2), Spring 2006 (2) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Hats off to Her-story auction (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Living Archives flyers (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 9th Table Talk - attendees and evaluation forms (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 9th Table Talk - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - 9th Table Talk - Conversations Continued kickoff cocktail party packets (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
- 2007
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Course lists, degree program descriptions, informational pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies board meeting minutes, members (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - General Correspondence
    - 2007 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter, Fall 2007 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous event and scholarship information flyers (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Living Archives flyers (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 10th Table Talk (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Nobel Women's Initiative conference report, related correspondence, and promotional material (Box 3, Folder 30)
- 2008
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Women's Studies communication campaign (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Meeting minutes, public relations proposal (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - General Correspondence
    - 2008 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Newsletters
    - Women's Studies newsletter - Fall 2008 (2); Friends of Women's Studies newsletter - Mar., Sept., Oct. 2008 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Gender creativity and new longevity, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Living Archives (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - 11th Table Talk (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Thrive photos and CDs (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
    - Thrive - University of Houston, Women's Studies program (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Clippings and Publications
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3, Folder 41)
- 2009
  - UH Women's Studies Academic and Business Documents
    - Informational pamphlets, degree programs, campus environment survey (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Friends of Women's Studies business Documents
    - Meeting minutes, member lists, communications plan (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - Collection development policy, processed collections list, draft of "XXamining gender: a tour of UH's Women's Archive and Research Center" - UH Alumni Quarterly (Winter 2009), WARC fact sheet (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Women's Studies and Friends of Women's Studies Financial Documents
    - WARC budget printouts (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - General Correspondence
    - 2009 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Newsletters
    - Friends of Women's Studies newsletter - Jan., Mar., Sep., Oct., Nov., Dec. (2) (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous event and scholarship flyers and invitations (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Living Archives flyers and spreadsheet of all Living Archives events (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - 12th Table Talk (Box 3, Folder 50)
- 2010
  - Friends of Women's Studies Business Documents
    - Friends of Women's Studies membership letter (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Women's Archives and Research Center
    - WARC pamphlet, update, and fundraising plan (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Newsletters
    - Friends of Women's Studies newsletter - Mar., Apr., Oct., Dec. (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - Miscellaneous flyers and invitations for events (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Living Archives (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - 13th Table Talk (Box 3, Folder 56)
- 2011-2012
  - General Correspondence
    - 2011-2012 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Newsletters
    - Friends of Women's Studies newsletter - Feb., Mar., Apr., Jun. (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Events, Programs, and Scholarships
    - 14th Table Talk (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Fast Friends (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Various UH events (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Living Archives - Tina Knowles/Joanne King Herring (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified event photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 63-64)